<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI.2><text><body><div1 n="1" type="Book" org="uniform" sample="complete"><p><milestone unit="card" n="1" />
<milestone n="1" ed="p" unit="line" />The wrath sing,  goddess, of Peleus' son, Achilles, that destructive wrath which brought countless woes upon the Achaeans, and sent forth to Hades many valiant souls of heroes, and made them themselves spoil for dogs and every bird; thus the plan of Zeus came to fulfillment,<milestone n="5" ed="p" unit="line" />from the time when<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">1</note> first they parted in strife Atreus' son, king of men, and brilliant Achilles.
Who then of the gods was it that brought these two together to contend?  The son of Leto and Zeus; for he in anger against the king roused throughout the host an evil pestilence, and the people began to perish,<milestone n="10" ed="p" unit="line" />because upon the priest Chryses the son of Atreus had wrought dishonour. For he had come to the swift ships of the Achaeans to free his daughter, bearing ransom past counting; and in his hands he held the wreaths of Apollo who strikes from afar,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="yes" place="unspecified">2</note> on a staff of gold; and he implored all the Achaeans,<milestone n="15" ed="p" unit="line" />but most of all the two sons of Atreus, the marshallers of the people: <quote>Sons of Atreus, and other well-greaved Achaeans, to you may the gods who have homes upon <placeName key="tgn,7011019" authname="tgn,7011019">Olympus</placeName> grant that you sack the city of Priam, and return safe to your homes; but my dear child release to me, and accept the ransom<milestone n="20" ed="p" unit="line" />out of reverence for the son of Zeus, Apollo who strikes from afar.</quote>
Then all the rest of the Achaeans shouted assent, to reverence the priest and accept the glorious ransom, yet the thing did not please the heart of Agamemnon, son of Atreus, but he sent him away harshly, and laid upon him a stern command:<milestone n="25" ed="p" unit="line" /><quote>Let me not find you, old man, by the hollow ships, either tarrying now or coming back later, lest your staff and the wreath of the god not protect you. Her I will not set free. Sooner shall old age come upon her in our house, in <placeName key="perseus,Argos" authname="perseus,Argos">Argos</placeName>, far from her native land,<milestone n="30" ed="p" unit="line" />as she walks to and fro before the loom and serves my bed.  But go, do not anger me, that you may return the safer.</quote></p></div1></body></text></TEI.2>